Hi everybody, welcome back to the channel.
And today is the final episode of our
Turkish ice cream so super stretchy ice
cream little bit of science not too much
we're going to make a luxury Dondurma.
So yeah, part three we did part one where
we made it with traditional ingredients, had to
try and adjust the manufacturing stage because
we just don't have the the tools available to
hand at home, stage two or part two was making
a recipe that I found online from a chef in the
Philippines that was shockingly bad, possibly one
of the worst ice creams I've ever made, and part
three which is this one, we're not going to go
too deep into the history because we've done two
parts of this Dondurma already. So part three,
let's very briefly talk about what makes Turkish
ice cream stretchy. So salep root, that orchid
flower, it's the powdered root or dried powdered
and then added into the dairy base that makes it
stretchy. Some parts of the world use mastic
as well to help boost that stretchiness,
it does a little bit to a degree but I don't think
we really need to use that and it's just something
else that you don't need to buy as well. So
what makes Turkish Orchid root or salep orchid
root stretchy? When you break it down, in the
salp root flour that Turkish Orchid root flour,
is a polysaccharide. A polysaccharide is a
carbohydrate that is essentially multiple types
of sugar or multiple sugar molecules bonded
together. Now the polysaccharide in Turkish
Orchid root flour is glucomannan, we are quite
lucky these days that we can buy glucomannan,
we can buy this extracted from other
other places so this has likely come
from an elephant tuber or what's commonly known
as Konjac root, it's a type of yam so for other
parts of the world it's a type of sweet
potato if you will. It's processed,
it's got exactly the same components we don't
have to tear down all those Orchid root flowers
we can go for this, this is mass produced stuff so
what we're going to do is we're going to create a
luxury dondurma ice cream ,we're going to treat
it slightly differently, we're going to try and
treat it in exactly the same way we do any other
ice cream but we're going to stretch it or we're
going to perform the stretch the beat & stretch
right at the end before we serve it up. So what
are we going to need for our final part for our
final episode of Turkish dondurma ice cream?
We are going to need 450g of milk, 350g of cream,
120g of sugar, 40g of dextrose, 40g of skim milk
powder and 4g of glucomannan. Okay so let's
get everything ready right here, so this is
nice and easy we've got our milk and our cream in
here in here we have our sugar our dextrose and
our glucomannan so we're just going to stir this
together and we're just going to pour it straight
into there and this is our skim milk powder. We'll
pour that in there as well give this a nice bit of
a stir and let's get it on the hob, and for this
ice cream we are going to use a vanilla bean,
I don't know if that's an authentic flavor, maybe
let me know in the comments. I know rose water
was and mastic is an authentic flavor but we're
going to splash out and use a vanilla bean so
whilst that's on the hob heating up we're going
to split our vanilla bean in half and we're going
to scrape out the seeds or the caviar depending
on what you want to call it I just call it seeds,
and we're going to put the whole thing in the
pot and with our vanilla bean and the seeds
in there we're going to stir this and bring it up
to a nice high temperature of 85 to 90 C which is
185-195°F. We need to bring it up to the higher
temperature than normal because glucomannan is
actually a type of starch and most starches need
higher temperatures than a lot of the stabilizers
that we use to activate completely. We
don't normally do this but we're going
to leave this in the in the pan and we're just
going to stir it for a few minutes, we want to
make sure that everything's completely dissolved.
You don't need to turn this into a gel before you
churn, its stabilizers (including starches) will
continue to transform as they're cooling down,
like everything, it thickens as it gets cooler
and that's just the way ice cream recipes and a
lot of other recipes work. The heat agitates
the molecules and allows them to move more
freely and as they start to cool down, molecules
get slower so we're going to leave this here and
after a few minutes we're going to pour this in
a container and pop it in the fridge overnight.
So after your ice cream base is completely
homogenized and all mixed together,
pop it in a container and put it in the
fridge. You need to get this really chilled
down well so overnight. Then after that
we're going to take it out of the fridge,
fish out our vanilla bean and give it a really
good stir because it's going to be quite viscous,
then pour it into your ice cream machine and
get it running as normal. After 10 minutes it'll
be ready to scoop out and put it in the freezer.
It's been in the freezer overnight, we're going to
leave this this out much like we did in the other
versions we're going to leave this out to warm up
a bit because one thing we established is that the
um Turkish ice cream sellers on the street their
ice cream is served at a much higher temperature
than what it would be straight out of freezer so
there it is we're going to leave this out for a
good 5 or 10 minutes and once we do that we're
going to get our cezve and Turkish coffee and
get some brewed up. So to make our Turkish coffee
we're going to take two cups worth of water, these
are little espresso cups, and two tablespoons of
our Turkish coffee, super fine powder, get it on
heat. Ideally use gas if you can but I don't have
it so here we go. After 1 or 2 minutes you're
going to see this and then after another couple
of minutes it's going to start doing this at
that stage you're going to take it off and let
it come back up to that boil again before you
pour it into your cup keeping all that crema.
So with our Turkish coffee poured, there are
different names for the type of Turkish coffee
or the the serving type I should say depending
on the amount of sugar, there is no sugar in
this one so I wanted to make sure that we had
the actual flavor of this real Turkish coffee.
Turkish coffee is ground ultra fine so much finer
than espresso powder is so that now needs to sit
for 2 to 3 minutes apparently so we can get rid
of this. Something else that I wanted to touch on
was Turkish ice cream and Turkish coffee Turkish
coffee was often served with something like you
know a Turkish delight or a small sweet treat so
we have here Pişmaniye, pronunciation is probably
shocking but as good as it's going to get, so let
let's open these up we've got two of those. Looks
like rock wall insulation, I think it's made
by spun sugar and flour but um I will confirm
that on the screen so let's put that there make
sure that doesn't melt by touching our Cup oh
oh it's....
tasty.
Now final stage of the whole Turkish three part
series, we're going to start processing our ice
cream. Now if you remember from the first
and the second parts of this, we need to get
in there and mix it up we already know that
we've got a really good amount of stretch so
we're going to increase that stretch now just
by manipulating it for a couple of minutes.
So I started doing this with a spoon but it was
just too hard to do as you can see I've put in
some serious effort, so out come the gloves
we're going to get our gloves on and get our
hands in there the heat from our hands will really
make this process much easier don't go too mad,
just do a minute or two and this is what you're
left with.... after 2 minutes of manipulation
got in there with a pair of gloves on get that
extra heat from my hands just to bring it up
to a reasonable serving temperature like I said I
think this is served somewhere around - 9°C - 10°C
it allows the starches to reform and create that
stretch so let's just put some in a bowl so just
in case as we're filming this whole thing is not
about the taste we know that we can make ice cream
taste good, it's about that stretch so you've seen
on the thumbnail how stretchy this stuff actually
is look at it it's really good this is exactly as
you would expect it to be, plus we've got a really
really good combination of ingredients
It tastes incredible, it's not gummy,
beautiful vanilla flavor, perfect stretchy Turkish
ice cream dondurma without salep flour, without
mastic. We've got our Turkish sweets here I think
these are also from Syria but unusual texture,
very nice though ....stuck to the cup thought
it would. Very nice.... ah man I'm making a
mess and finally to finish off our Turkish ice
cream series, some Turkish coffee..... that is
delicious. So as it say in Turkey
Şerefe
Thanks very much for watching, don't forget
to like and subscribe I'll see you next time.